Welcome to Consortium News CN Live. I'm
Kathy Vogen.
>> And I'm Joe Lauria, the editor-inchief
of Consortium News. We're back again to
discuss the case of Dan Dugen, an
Australian pilot, former US Marine
aviator who the United States wants
Australia to extradite for allegedly
breaking a US arms embargo against
China. A grand jury indictment filed and
sealed in 2017 and discussed on the
occasion of Anthony Blinkin's October
2023 visit to Australia accuses Dugen of
providing military training to Chinese
pilots at the Test Flying Academy of
South Africa without obtaining
permission from the US State Department.
The indictment also accuses Dugen of
involvement in a conspiracy to
retransfer the ownership of a plane, a
1960s era T2 Buckeye to the Academy
where it would be used for training
aircraft carrier landings. Dugen lawyers
say this happened way before Dougen's
training was conducted. The indictment
lists multiple offenses including
moneyaundering from the proceeds of his
alleged crime. Dougen left the US
Marines in 2002 and moved to Australia
where he set up a business of joy rides
for tourists called Top Gun Australia.
10 years later, he became an Australian
citizen and abandoned his US citizenship
on Australia Day, January 26th, 2012.
Dugen claims and his flight log
allegedly shows that his casual training
gigs for the South African school, a
total of 18 hours work, took place after
he ceased being a US citizen. It is also
claimed by the defense that the impuged
school's curriculum is entirely
comprised of open-source material. The
Dugen was training civilians on how to
cope with difficult conditions such as
engine stall and landing in mountainous
areas such as Tibet. Most surprisingly,
the defense reveals that the alleged
Chinese aircraft carrier used for
Dugen's training was still under
construction. thousands of miles away at
the time of his lessons.
>> Conservative News reported live from the
Dugen courtroom last week where his
defense argued that because what he's
alleged to have done was not a crime in
Australia at the time the lessons were
conducted that it should prevent the
Australian attorney general from sending
Dougen to the United States because
Australia's extradition treaty with the
US requires such dual criminality. None
of Dougen's fellow Australian trainers
have been charged with any crime in
Australia, for instance. In their
written submissions, the defense argued
that the United States had no sovereign
control over Dugen by the time he
trained the Chinese pilots because he
had become an Australian citizen by
then, and that his alleged involvement
in a conspiracy to obtain the school's
plane was pure fiction, conveniently
construed to indict him for conduct
while he was still a citizen of the US.
Dugen was arrested and imprisoned by
Australia's federal police three years
ago and placed in solitary confinement
for the first 19 months as a high-risk
prisoner. It was 62 days before he found
out why. We spoke previously with
Dugen's wife Saffne about the
catastrophic emotional and financial
impact this has had on their six
children. Today we want to delve into
the legal and political issues. Please
welcome the Australian Senator David
Shoubridge, a former barristister and
John Kiryaku, the CIA whistleblower on
torture who has submitted an affidavit
in the Dugen case. Senator Schub Dugen's
defense has requested that the
extradition be refused. They say there
should never have been a section 19
extradition eligibility hearing because
the attorney general should have applied
the dual criminality test a long time
ago and ruled out the extradition. The
defense highlighted a conflict between
the extradition treaty and Australia's
extradition act. The treaty demands
contemporaneous dual criminality at the
time of the offending conduct whereas
the act demands it at the time an
extradition request is received. Why is
that important to this case?
>> Yeah, this came aart this came about
because of an amendment to Australia's
extradition laws around about a decade
ago which at the time appeared to be
fairly benign. No one really noticed it.
It wasn't highlighted. Um and that
changed the moment at which you consider
the dual criminality um being you know
if somebody who is in Australia is going
to be sent to another country to face
criminal proceedings which is what
extradition permits
um our sense of basic justice says well
we shouldn't be sending someone from
Australia to another country to face
criminal proceedings if if what they're
alleged to have done um isn't a crime
against Australia. his statute books. I
mean, I'll give you a very obvious
example. Um, there are many countries
around the world that shamefully still
criminalize same-sex um relationships.
And there may be countries around the
world where that's a crime. Um, it would
be, you know, appalling an appalling
concept that a country would seek to
extradite or successfully extradite
someone from Australia to face
prosecution in a third country for the
crime of being in a same-sex marriage
when that is legal. and you know 100%
supported by our human rights
frameworks. Um so I mean that's at the
core of the extradition
treaties that Australia enters into.
There are other tests such as is there a
fair judicial process? Can we have faith
in the systems and the like. Um but but
of course you know things change over
time. Something that wasn't criminal 20
years ago may become criminal now. Um
you think about how our laws have
changed to respond to um increasing
concerns about child sexual abuse and
there's been a bunch of laws that have
come in to deal with that. Our laws have
changed in relation to a number of
issues that have come about because of
new technology. And so we have things
that are against the law now that were
not criminal 20 years ago or 30 years
ago. And one of the other basic rules
about our criminal justice system is you
can only be penalized under our law for
things that were um criminalized at the
time you did them. The parliament can
pass criminal laws to make conduct
illegal, but it should only operate from
the time the law passes into the future.
You don't retrospectively make things
illegal in Australia because you're
meant to be able to operate, you know,
within the laws as we understand them.
And you don't want you don't want
parliaments I can assure you you don't
want you know me and others making
things retrospectively criminal
criminalizing conduct you did in the
past that wasn't criminal at the time.
So two basic concepts under the
extradition laws
um we're only meant to be extraditing
people when something is contrary to our
law and contrary to the law of the
country that's trying to extradite them.
It has to be a crime the conduct needs
to be criminal in both jurisdictions.
And then there's this absolutely
fundamental concept in our law that you
don't make things retrospectively
illegal. You don't make things illegal
in the past if you know if they weren't
at the time because people have a right
to you know run their lives, organize
their affairs in light of the laws as
they stand at the time, not not what
some future parliament might judge them.
But you see what the parliament snuck
through in amendments to the extradition
act about a decade ago was they said,
"Well, look, yep, sure." Um, if
someone's going to be extradited, then
it needs to be criminal conduct both in
the country that's seeking the
extradition and in Australia. Tick. Um,
but we're not going to be so troubled
about whether or not it was criminal at
the time the the conduct happened in
Australia. We're going to let that ride
and we're going to allow the parliament
to pass new laws, make things illegal
now, which weren't illegal at the time
the conduct was happened. And and
provided those laws have been passed by
the time the third country seeks the
extradition, if it's illegal just at the
time the paperwork is filed, and in Dan
Dugen's case, it was the better part of
a decade, you know, after the conduct.
They said, "Provided it's illegal at the
time that the paperwork is filed, then
no worries. we'll send them off to
America. And you know, not only is that
contrary to the treaty that we signed on
extradition, it's also contrary to that
basic principle that Australia is not
going to punish you for conduct that
wasn't illegal at the time you did it
according to our laws. Um, and yet all
of this has been run rough shot over in
the Dugen case. Um, and I would have
hoped the attorney general would have
taken a pretty hard view on this, either
the former one or the current one, and
said, "Well, actually, we're not going
to be sending someone to face criminal
prosecution in the United States for
something that wasn't a crime under
Australian law at the time they're
alleged to have done it. That affronts
our sense of justice." I tell you what,
it affronts my sense of justice. Yeah,
that's what's happening in the Dan Dugen
case.
>> Well, this is right. But I mean there's
even this element in American law as
well as as John Kiryaku will be able to
confirm. But there has to be
foreseeability
that something is a crime. And that is
something that that's there's a parallel
there between the case of Dugen and
Julian Assange.
um because article 7 in um European
Convention on Human Rights equated to
more or less to the fifth amendment does
specify that somebody has to know it's a
crime before they think of conducting uh
that behavior. The other thing of course
is uh the first amendment and in the
submissions of Kery Law who is defending
uh Dan Dugen. They mentioned these
motivational talks that he gave in China
in the corporate environments you know
inspiring teams to succeed all that kind
of thing. If he went to America that
could be considered a violation of his
first amendment rights, free speech
rights. But hang on a second. Dugen is
exactly like Assange. He is now a
foreign citizen who acted abroad and
according to Justice Kavanaaugh's rule
in the Supreme Court in 2020, June 2020,
he articulated what he called
longestablished laws that foreign
nationals who acted abroad don't have
rights to any constitutional protection.
So, you know, Dugen is having a really
hard time. There's no defense at the
grand jury stage, only prosecutors. He's
not allowed to argue the facts of the
case in Australia. And then possibly
over there, and why wouldn't that be a
second deal breaker that he wouldn't
have any constitutional rights cuz he's
no longer a US citizen?
Well, as you know, that question of um
equality before the law was a key issue
in the extradition of Julian Assange.
His legal team said, "Well, if the US
government um won't agree that a non- US
citizen has access to the same
constitutional rights as a US citizen in
criminal law proceedings, well, then
that was a very potential, you know,
barrier to uh Julian being extradited
from the UK to the US because it
affronts that concept of equality before
the law.
>> Um, you know, those if those same
concerns arise in Dan Dugen's case,
well, then you'd hope that's a matter
the courts will take into account in
considering whether or not to permit an
extradition in Australia because
equality before the law, you think, is a
pretty fundamental thing. We shouldn't
be sending Australian citizens to any
jurisdiction to face criminal
prosecutions where they have only half
the rights or a whole bunch of rights
are missing um to allow them to defend
themselves when you know a citizen of
the United States would have a a far
greater set of rights under criminal
law. So, if our attorney general should
never permit the extradition of an
Australian citizen to the United States,
if the United States says, "Well,
actually, sure, you know, send them back
to our country. Uh, we'll we'll whack
them before the criminal courts. Um, and
we won't afford them any constitutional
protections. Um, you know, we won't
afford them the same rights that US
citizens have because we want to whack
them in jail." I mean, that should that
you would think should never happen. Um,
but it doesn't seem that those pretty
fundamental issues have ever really
troubled the mind of either this or the
former attorney general. And I find that
quite problematic. Um, but but you know,
ultimately
it's for the courts to make these
decisions based upon how they understand
the law to be. Um, I can't, you know,
I'm I'm not going to try and substitute
my personal views for the views of the
court, but these are some pretty
fundamental issues. Will the courts
permit somebody to be extradited
um when the alleged conduct that they're
said to have engaged in was not against
the law at the time, against Australian
law at the time they engaged in. I think
that's a pretty fundamental issue. Will
the court say that the Extradition Act
as passed by the Commonwealth Parliament
um is is a valid piece of legislation
um if the act is contrary to the
provisions of the treaty um because it's
only through the treaty and the extra
external affairs power that the
Commonwealth has the power um to pass
this act. And if the legislation is
contrary to the treaty um well the
courts are going to have to determine
whether or not the legislation was valid
in whole or in part to make that change.
Um again, you know, it's for the courts
to make these decisions on
constitutional law, not for myself. But
I think there is a separate political
question here, which is should the
attorney general, who ultimately is a
politician and is meant to be
representing Australian values, you
know, you know, in light of but making
political judgments separate to the
legal system. Should the attorney
general have ever signed u the paperwork
to permit the extradition?
You know, I think the more we look into
the case, the more there are compelling
reasons why that shouldn't have
happened. Um, you know, and of course,
one of the other one of the other issues
in this is the United States is is
saying that their criminal law applies
to conduct committed anywhere on the
planet.
And you know, they did that in the
Assange case as well. They said we can
pass laws in relation to our national
security that apply anywhere on the
planet. Now there are some areas where
where states accept that extra
territoriality like you know there are
occasions where you need to say well
states can have their criminal laws
extend beyond their borders because
there's some conduct you you really want
to capture and traditionally that's been
um conduct like piracy. you know, piracy
at the high seas doesn't happen in any
any country's jurisdiction. If you're
going to have bring have criminal
proceedings to bring that to account,
well, you need extra territoriality. Um,
slavery, you know, slavery often happens
um um uh through third countries or, you
know, again, you know, people are
transported on the high seas. You
traditionally have extr territoriality
to deal with that. But are we going to
permit the United States to just say any
part of their criminal law um wherever
they choose can apply to anyone on the
planet wherever they are? You know, I
think there's got to be boundaries here
and the Dugen case again is showing that
our government should be standing up for
some of those boundaries to protect
Australian citizens from the, you know,
imperial reach of the United States
criminal law.
>> Senator Schubbridge, what is going on
here? Really, I have two questions
really. How does this fit in or does it
fit in to the continuous pressure the
United States has been putting on
Australia to make China an enemy when
China is not an enemy of the of
Australia? And why did the attorney
general go along with this as you were
just saying?
>> Well, I mean, three questions really,
aren't there? Why did we change the
laws? You know, you know, there seemed
to be no compelling reason to change the
extradition laws to permit a Dugen
extradition, right? So I'm I'm yet to to
that happened before my time in federal
parliament. I've looked into it. There's
no compelling reason that was put
forward to change the laws at the time.
And I think that's a mystery that's
still yet to be explained. Um why does
our attorney general agree to US
extradition requests and why do they
often show so little resistance to US
actions? Well, I think you know anyone
who's observed Australia's international
relations over the last five decades
would say that we are incredibly plant
to the United States. You know, many of
our foreign policy settings aren't
really set in CRA. They're they're
rubber stamped in CRA, but they're set
in Washington and we do what we're told.
Um, and this appears to be, you know,
very consistent with that pattern. It
doesn't really matter whether it's Labor
or the coalition. You know, they sign on
to this Australia's place in the world
is to sort of meekly, politely, and
sometimes at incredible expense follow
what the United States tells us to do.
And you know, it's another brick in the
wall that I think is being built um to
make the case for Australia to have a
genuinely independent foreign and
defense policy and start making some of
these decisions ourselves. But you know
in the context of a lot of the rhetoric
that's been coming out of Washington,
it's been pared in Canberra, you know,
the capital of Australia. And you hear
it come from our security community, the
defense,
AIO, and all of our security agencies.
You know, they are desperately trying to
persuade the Australian public that we
should join the United States if they
choose to go to war with China. and you
know, opening up Australia's real estate
to new and expanded US military bases,
make our armed forces interoperable with
the United States so that we can just
slot in as a little dependent unit of a
larger US military deployment. Um, make
our procurement almost entirely
dependent on US military equipment. um
which of course creates a substantial
sovereignty risk if the United States
ever chooses not to support our defense
equipment in the future. You know, there
are all these decisions being made, you
know, and separate to that is this
massive orcus mess which is tying us
into having US and UK designed and
largely built nuclear submarines over
the next four decades at a cost a
staggering cost from an Australian's
perspective of like 375 billion
Australian dollars. like it's all of
these decisions are being made. Um and
they all take us down the same path,
increasing dependence on the United
States, less sovereign decision making
about our future being made in
Australia. And I think it's an
incredibly dangerous and reckless path
that the current administration, a Labor
Party, the previous administration, the
coalition, um have been taking this on
for decades now. I don't think there's a
good answer to this question and it
applies to a country like Germany as
well where German leaders do things that
absolutely hurt German interests but
serve American interests. Why are
Australian leaders doing this when it
hurts Australia? Uh that's maybe an
impossible question to answer. There's
lots of theories.
>> You see, you're asking some of your
theories are
>> you're you're asking questions that
never never trouble their minds in CRA.
This is like a an accepted starting
point of the conversation. It's an a
priority assumption that our security
and our future is is intertwined and
imshed with the United States. And
you're not allowed to question that in
CRA. I would have thought you would know
this by now, Joe. You're not allowed to
question that a prior assumption because
once you start doing that, once you
start asking, well, hang on, why are we
doing this? You know, how is this making
Australia safe? you know, we live in one
of the most geopolitically benign parts
of the planet, right? There's the only
place really safer than Australia
um geopolitically is New Zealand, and
that's only because it's the other side
of Australia, right? Um apart from that,
Australia is in pretty much the most
benign part of the planet. We're
surrounded by oceans. We have, you know,
a um not just an ocean and a sea, but a
massive island archipelago separating us
from um Eurasia. Um the Pacific Ocean on
one side, the Indian Ocean on the other
side, Antarctica to the south of us. You
know, the the only country, you know,
place to be a kind of threat to us is
kind of New Zealand or Papa New Guinea,
right? And the we we live in an
incredibly benign part of the world,
right? So, so in order for us to be at
risk from some conflict with China, the
only way we can be at risk in a military
conflict with China is if we invite that
conflict to Australia, right? We we
actually say, "Hang on, here we are.
Don't forget about us. Make us a
target." You know, um, actively make us
one of your enemies. And the only way I
know to do that would be for us to
position a whole lot of United States
military bases on our shore which might
be used by the United States if they
wanted to have a war with China. Like
that would be the only way of putting us
at risk. And that's exactly what we are
doing. These bases aren't to protect us.
These bases are to protect the United
States interests. But the bases
themselves, our our dependence on the
United States, our unthinking support
for United States military deployments
in the region, they don't make us safe.
They are the only potential geopolitical
risk. They create the risk. They don't
create safety. They create risk. And you
know, but even saying that, you know, or
thinking that, um, it's like the third
rail of Australian politics. You're not
allowed to say it. You're not allowed to
think it. You just have to believe.
Like, you know, you wake up in the
morning and you believe in, you know,
your own personal deity, your own
personal savior, you also have to
believe unthinkingly and with faith in
the United States alliance because it
gets a bit awkward if you start
critically thinking about it. Well,
except of your two former Australian
prime ministers, Malcolm Fraser, who
wrote Dangerous Allies, and of course,
Paul Keating, who has, you know, spoken
and batted off all of the attacks, uh,
you know, about us not needing these
submarines at all. In fact, a totally
different strategy of defense would be
more appropriate for us. I mean I I you
know there looking back on Malcolm
Fraser's time, Malcolm Fraser used to
put some a few the occasional red line
in to our relationship with the United
States. He for example wouldn't let US
nuclear armed B-52s come to Australia.
Um but otherwise Malcolm Fraser had very
much a pro- US
>> lean, pro- US alliance lean, but he put
some red lines in. Those red lines have
been totally white removed off the table
by the coalition and labor in the
decades since. And you know, I I admire
Paul Keading's robust opposition to
Orcus, you know, and it reflects my
views. It's it's not in Australia's
interest. Why the hell are we doing
this? You know, um but unfortunately
when he was prime minister, he was also
very robustly supporting and
unquestioningly supporting Australia's
military alliance with the United
States. you know, US military bases such
as Pine Gap and um you know, I like
people getting a sort of, you know, um
robust sense of independence once they
leave office, but bloody hell, it'd be
nice if occasionally they did it while
they were in office as well.
>> Yes, maybe like Goff Whitland, but look
what happened to him.
>> Thank you so much, David, for that
perspective on what's going on. poor Dan
Dugen, probably a porn in this whole
changing relationship between Australia
and China.
>> But uh let's hope that we get um an
outcome announced. The judgment was
reserved in the court. Uh, as I said,
the defense are seeking to have the
extradition request overturned, but uh
we may see it go to the high court if uh
if we don't get a satisfactory response.
>> Well, my feeling is either way it's
likely to find its way to the high
court. So, this is round one. And you
know, and I just in the when I say that,
I just think about all of the stress and
the anxiety and the cost that that puts
on Dan's family. you know, I know his
wife and his kids, uh, they're under an
incredible amount of stress. You know,
there's an Australian family here that's
literally being ripped apart by these
proceedings as well, and we shouldn't
forget them. So, you know,
>> I hope all Australians are thinking
about that. You know, what should our
government be doing? You got a family in
deep distress here, and you would have
hoped they're in an Australian family's
court, not in the United States
military's court, but you know, such is
life.
>> Okay. Thank you. Thank you, David.
>> Thank you. Thanks. Thanks, Joe. Thanks,
John. Sorry I can't stay around um for
the rest of it, but uh
>> that's okay. You've given us plenty of
time.
>> Cool.
>> Wow. John Kiryaku.
>> Um good to see you.
>> Good to see you. Thanks for coming on.
You have uh submitted an affidavit in
the uh Dugen case. Can you tell it? I
haven't had time to look at it um
because I just got my hands on it, but
uh can you tell us why? What's in there?
What what what can you attest to?
>> Sure. Well, this this actually
originated because of a series of
articles that I had written for
consortium news uh back in 2022 and 2023
about the dilletterious effects of uh
solitary confinement on the mental uh
well-being of American prisoners. I I
said that um that I had
not been subjected to to the level of of
uh solitary confinement that other many
other American prisoners had. I spent a
total of nine days in solitary
confinement. I needed to lose the weight
anyway at the time. I I joked, but the
truth is solitary confinement is used in
the United States unlike in any other
country in the world. it's used as a
form of punishment. And one thing that I
think almost no Americans realize is
that the concept of solitary confinement
as a punishment was actually created in
the United States. It was created, and I
say this in the affidavit, it was
invented in 1829
at the Eastern State Penitentiary in
Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. You can
still go to Eastern State and take a
tour. It's in ruins now. But uh there
were, you know, famous prisoners there
like Al Capone and and early murderers
and and uh people that we've read about
in history books. In any event, in 1829,
um,
American politicians came up with this
idea where they would build this
enormous imposing
neo gothic escape-proof maximum security
penitentiary made of stone. It had just
tiny little cells. The guards were in
the in the very center and and the the
cells went around in in spokes like
spokes of a wheel. The idea was that
each little tiny cell would have nothing
but a bed, a chair, a little table, a
small um chamber pot, and a Bible. with
the idea being that if a prisoner has
nothing to do all day long but eat and
sleep and read the Bible that he will
come out of prison at the end of his
sentence as a good law-abiding Christian
man.
And what they found was that instead
everybody went insane.
And that's where we first learned of
these severe psychological effects that
that solitary confinement has. It it
leads to anxiety, depression, paranoia,
hallucinations,
suicidal thoughts, suicidal actions. So,
we've known this for 200 years, and
we're still using it. And when I say
using it,
the United Nations has declared the
American use of solitary confinement to
be a form of torture. And the United
Nations has urged all member countries
to limit solitary confinement to a
maximum of 15 days. Well, here in the
United States, we've had people in
solitary confinement for as long as 44
years.
And so I gave some examples in this
affidavit. There was a a prisoner uh by
the name of Anthony Gay. He was severely
mentally ill. He was held in a prison in
uh in Colorado and placed in solitary
confinement right after his conviction.
Rather than being placed in a mental
hospital where he could have received
treatment for schizophrenia, which is
what he was suffering from, he was in
this small 6x10 ft cell 24 hours a day,
7 days a week. He became paranoid. He be
he began self-mutilating. He stabbed
himself in the eye with a razor blade.
He cut off pieces of his own flesh and
ate them. He cut out one of his
testicles and hung it on on the
doororknob of his cell and then he
stitched his scrotum closed with a
zipper that he had taken uh out of his
pants. He didn't even realize what he
was doing. In all, and and get this,
this is typical of American uh prisons.
In all, his 7-year sentence was
eventually extended to 97 years because
he kept doing these things and adding
time. And what was his crime? In 1993,
he was arrested and charged with
stealing a $1 bill out of a restaurant
tip jar.
97 years in prison and he did two
decades of it in solitary confinement.
So in the affidavit I I wrote about four
or five six of these different cases and
I said look because Dan Dugen is a
highprofile prisoner.
He's going to be placed in either
solitary confinement or in something
called a communications management unit
which is akin to solitary confinement
where the prisoner is completely cut off
from the outside world. And you know,
unless he's stronger than anybody else
that I've ever encountered in my life,
this is going to have that same kind of
dilitterious
effect emotionally, mentally uh on him
that it's had on uh on everybody else
who's gone through it.
>> Now, what do you think about what I was
talking about before with Senator
Shubbridge? Yeah. The thing that killed
the Assange case was that he would be
debarred from constitutional protection
by way of his nationality alone and that
was a red line for the British court. Uh
>> yes, I think that's the that's the
strongest argument and I would even add
one here in the United States and and
Joe, you know this as well as I do.
We've discounted um criminal intent in
this country. Did he intend to violate
the law? Obviously not. He likely didn't
even know there was a law that governed
this kind of thing. And even if he did,
he wasn't an American citizen.
So, it seems to me if the United States
is really serious about stopping, let's
say, the training of, I don't know,
undercover Chinese intelligence
officers, they would have asked the
Australians to arrest everybody who
worked at the flight school, everybody
who was training foreign nationals to
use these planes, or nobody.
But to arrest and then demand the
extradition of of just Dan Dugen,
that just stinks of politics.
>> Yes. And in fact, uh I believe it is the
fifth amendment, although I'm not a
total expert on American law, but the
the bar is reasonable certainty in terms
of this foreseeability.
You know, that any reasonable person
would have known this was a crime. and
and in fact there are plenty of
indications for Dugen that that it is
not a crime, you know, in his country of
citizenship. So,
>> no,
>> you're right. He may not have even
known.
And you know, another sad thing here is
the Australians have been so weak in the
face of US demands. So willing to roll
over so far that this man has been
imprisoned now for years.
For years.
>> Yeah.
>> And he's not even been charged with a
crime in Australia.
>> Three years. And and why I wish
Schubbridge was still here to ask if
maybe you know Kathy uh why did
Australia put him in solitary
confinement? I would imagine the
Americans asked him, but I don't know
that. Why?
>> Um well, I've first of all um as I said
in the intro, uh Dugen didn't learn for
62 days uh why he had been arrested. He
had no clue. He was clueless, which also
points towards his innocence. Uh, but I
imagine that the Americans would have
said he's quite literally a flight risk,
saying he's a pilot.
>> Ridiculous. No,
>> they could have put a a bracelet around
his ankle, of course. And
>> Sure.
>> But they, you know, I think it's all for
show. Just as an aside, Kathy, just as
an aside,
>> one of my cellmates at the Federal
Correctional Institution at Lorettto,
Pennsylvania, where I was incarc
incarcerated for 23 months, was an
Australian
national.
He was violent. He was a convicted
arsonist.
Um, and not just an arsonist. He shouted
to everybody in the in the Department of
Motor Vehicles in Buffalo, New York. I'm
going to come back here and burn this
place to the ground, even if people are
in it. And what did he do? He came back
and he burned the place to the ground.
He was never in solitary confinement. He
ran back to Australia to escape. the the
Australians arrested him at the request
of the United States. He was never held
in solitary confinement. He was finally
extradited to the US where he was placed
in a low security prison with me.
And then he just quietly did his five
years and and went home.
>> So what makes Dan Dugen so dangerous
>> when clearly he's not dangerous?
>> Yeah, that's right. But I mean like
Assange, he's a kind of a political
>> prisoner and case
>> in those cases uh as Stella Assange said
the punishment is the process.
>> Yes.
Yes.
>> I want to ask you John that was
fascinating that sorry that history you
gave 1829
>> I was just looked up that James Madison
died in 1836. So I mean the guy who
wrote the you know the constitution who
and all the rights that this country was
going to be different from the tyrannies
of Europe
>> and then in 1829 they came up with this
idea. But my question is why when they
saw that they went insane and they
weren't quoting scripture when they came
out.
>> They hadn't why did they continue this?
So clearly that wasn't the real meeting
was it?
>> That's a great question. That's a great
question and and the answer is because
they decided that it was still effective
as a form of punishment. Maybe the
rehabilitation part didn't work, but by
God, nobody wanted to be in solitary,
and so that was a good punishment.
>> Has it worked as a deterrent?
>> Absolutely not.
>> No,
>> no. It's just cruel, that's all.
>> Uh, John, have you been following the
case as it's been going through the
courts? Um,
>> I have, and I've spoken to Sephrine.
I've spoken to to Dan's uh legal team in
Australia and to his US attorneys. I've
met them a couple of times here in
Washington. Uh they believe that they
have a very strong case. But as in the
case of Julian Assange or the case of
John Kuryaku or anybody else who faces
long periods of time in a in a
penitentiary, you might have a a strong
case, but an American jury would convict
a bologn sandwich, as the old saying
goes. And you're free to appeal, but you
have to appeal postconviction,
>> which means you do all the time first
while your appeal winds its way through
the courts. This is a no-win situation.
So, it has to be nipped in the bud, so
to speak. Three-year delay in in the
nipping of the bud. Uh on the Australia
side, if he's extradited to the US, he's
lost. And I'll tell you another thing,
too.
if he if he is extradited to the US and
convicted or extradited to the US and
takes a plea to a lesser charge, which
would still be a felony, he would be
banned from visiting the United States
for the next 25 years, but he has eight
brothers and sisters, and his parents
are still alive, and all of them live in
the United States.
>> Oh, I didn't know that. I mean, he's got
six children as well,
>> right?
>> A big family.
>> They He has an enormous family and he
would literally never get to see them
again unless they visited him in
Australia
>> and his parents are quite elderly and
they're not going to Australia.
>> Yeah.
>> Let me ask you, John, of two things.
One,
I want to ask you in general about grand
juries because there are some people in
Australia who really insensed about
this. We are used to it here in the US.
the idea of a grand jury that it is a
secret. It's always secret and it always
remains sealed. You're not supposed to
leak anything for it happens,
>> right?
>> How democratic of a of a of of a process
is it? Grand jury. Why did that happen
in the United States? If you know the
history of that, I'd be interested. And
and why is it so useful to the
authorities? You know, I I don't know
the history of it, but I can give you my
own experience with the grand jury. I
was arrested in January of 2012 and
charged with five felonies, including
three counts of espionage.
And um I hadn't been indicted by any
grand jury. And so when I went to meet
my attorneys the first time, one of them
said, "Well, wait a minute. Wait a
minute. What do you mean you've not been
indicted?" And I said, "No, they
arrested me and they took me in for
arraignment. I pleaded not guilty, but I
I've not been indicted by any grand
jury. So, they my attorneys went to the
justice department and said, "What is
this? Some kind of a some kind of a
circus?"
They said, "Fine. You want him indicted?
We'll indict him." This is where I
learned about the grand jury system.
They just called a group of people
together. It's like 30 people. And they
um they laid out their case. We had no
idea the grand jury was meeting. You're
not informed. Uh you're not allowed to
speak even if you were informed. You're
not allowed to sit in. You're not
allowed to ask questions. You're not
allowed to do anything. You have no
role. They just give their side of the
story and they say, "Okay, who wants to
indict and send him to trial?" Show of
hands. And of course, all 30 are going
to say, "Oh yeah, this sounds awful."
Espionage. Yes. Uh, you know, classified
information. Yes. Yes. Indict. Well,
they accidentally
leaked the transcript of the grand jury
to us.
And so, I got to see who my friends
really were and who my enemies really
were. I got to see them by name, former
co-workers, colleagues, people I
considered to be friends. And I got to
read every single word that they said
about me.
Well, the bottom line is no one stands a
chance before a grand jury. Not a
chance.
It was ugly.
>> An opportunity to what they thought was
complete secrecy. They unloaded on you
people.
>> And you know what, Joe? One of them, you
know, I've I've become kind of well
known uh not just in the United States,
but around the world over the last two
years or so only because I've somehow
hit the sweet spot in the in the YouTube
algorithm. And I was on Joe Rogan last
week at 2 and a half million views. I I
have a couple of shorts out that have
30, 35, 38 million views.
Well, all of a sudden, some of these
people are reaching out to me, hey, we
should do something together. We should
do a speaking tour together. Oh, why
don't we have a debate? It's like, do
you think I don't know what you said
about me on March the 6th, 2012?
Because I know exactly what you said
about me, and now you want me to be your
friend. You want me to help you make
money?
No, thank you.
>> That's that was a unique opportunity to
learn that kind of thing. Sometimes I
think if I I'd like to die and then
still be able to see what people are
saying about me, you know, read
now. You got that chance.
>> But but it's better to see what they're
saying about you when you're down.
>> Oh, and when you're still alive, too,
cuz now you can get back in it.
>> That's right. That's right.
>> I mean, Kathy, before I turn it back to
you, this Why did this take 15 years
with Doug? And I mean, this this stuff
happened a long time ago. They only
indicted him like several years after,
six years after that. And then
>> nothing's happened until Lincoln shows
up.
>> The Secretary of State, this shows how
political it is. Coming to shore up
Australia that they're not getting weak
need against China. All of a sudden,
that's when Unbelievable.
>> That's it right there. That's it right
there. Joe, you hit it on the head. This
is about China. This is about a
political scalp to show that we're tough
against China. There was an indictment
here in Washington just a week ago, two
weeks ago. Uh a former um intelligence
officer indicted for allegedly uh
passing some sort of analysis to to
China. He swears he's innocent. He he
was an employee of a think tank, former
like naval intelligence or DIA or
something like that. Uh but this is
about China. And another thing too, and
forgive me if if you've heard me say
this a million times because I have said
it a million times, but these these
attorneys, these assistant US attorneys
in the in the Department of Justice,
they don't get promoted by not
prosecuting you, right? They don't get
promoted by not trying to, you know, get
you some draconian sentence. They all
want to be US attorney. They all want to
run for Congress or run for governor or
have the corner office in the a the
alevel uh uh law firm, the big law firm.
And so they're going to make that career
on your back. And I think that's what
we're seeing here. I think that somebody
just went through some old files and
said, "Hey, I might be able to make this
case." And then we can just say it's a
China espionage case, right? And so
what? This guy, this guy doesn't even
love America. They probably said he gave
up his American citizenship. What kind
of American is that? I'm going to go
after him and make a name for myself.
>> And then we have the case.
>> I hate to be so cynical, but I mean th
those were the attitudes that I
encountered at the Justice Department.
>> Yeah,
>> Kathy.
>> Well, um I don't have anything really
more to say. Let's just wait and see
what the result of this uh federal court
hearing is. Uh we had uh we had a
strange argument going on there about
you know when um the dual criminality
kicks in, you know, or the absence of
dual criminality kicks in. Prosecution
was saying, "Oh, it doesn't matter. We
can let somebody languish in prison for
2 years before even having an
eligibility hearing." uh it doesn't
matter, you know, whereas the defense is
saying, as soon as someone is arrested,
it has to be deemed immediately. We've
got to move to action straight away to
determine whether this is an
extraditable offense, whether this is an
extraditable person, whether there's
dual criminality. So, uh you know, it it
was a very odd argument. I think that
the defense did a fantastic job and uh
the the prosecution it was so full of
sections and subsections it was really
quite difficult to follow. Um but we'll
see. We'll see. Presently, but might
take a couple of weeks before the
judgment comes out. And that judgment
could be that the eligibility hearing
that took place last year, a section 19
hearing they call it, uh which
determined that he was eligible for
extradition that it will be overturned
as the defense request. There's another
story here that I should tell you. um is
that Dugen had changed his lawyers,
right? And so when this section 19
hearing came up, his new lawyers, which
is Collery Law, Bernard Collery, the
former attorney general of the
Australian Capital Territory, those guys
hadn't had enough time to study the
case. And they asked the judge for more
time to, you know, get on top of it and
put forward the right arguments. And the
judge refused. And so that when they
they said, "Well, we've got no arguments
to put forth today." And so the judge
deemed him eligible for extradition.
That's a bit weird. So
>> yeah, that sounds like pressure from the
US.
>> Oh, whatever. Whatever. But it just
doesn't sound like bonafide uh due
process to me. And
>> yeah, I agree.
>> A scout to show that we're tough on
China. And they even get to judge
somewhere. The judge goes along with
this. an Australian judge is not it's
it's beyond words this um
>> they'll do a person yeah a person's life
if it serves up
>> yeah I want to say one other thing very
quickly I I understand we're over time
but um Sephrine
uh Dan's wife Sephne has been so
steadfast in her support how this woman
has been able to support her husband
with the energy that she has, raise six
kids, try not to lose their farm, engage
with attorneys, engage with a a public
relations person, um find American
attorneys, lobby politicians. I She's
like a superwoman. And I think that that
when he wins this thing, and I really
believe that he'll win, it's because of
her.
Oh, she was in a very
bad way when we we talked to her just
just a few days before the last hearing.
And you know, she when she started off,
you know, she she almost broke down
immediately, but she she is able to pull
herself together and speak sensibly and
intelligently about it. So, you know,
>> she's fantastic. Wonderful.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you, John. Thank you, John.
>> Thank you. Good to see you both.
>> Okay.
>> Yes. Thank you. Bye.